BU Records: Alumni Rebuilding Campaign, Inclusive: 1922 February-1923, undated, Bulk: 1922 March-May, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
BU Records: Alumni Rebuilding Campaign
Inclusive: 1922 February-1923, undated, Bulk: 1922 March-May, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
BU/58
Rebuilding Campaign
Alumni Rebuilding Campaign Committee
2 document boxes.
The BU Records: Alumni Rebuilding Campaign consist of correspondence, financial documents, and administrative records regarding fundraising efforts to rebuild the F. L. Carroll Chapel and Library after the building was destroyed by fire in 1922.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Average.
Biography/Profile
On 1922 February 11, the dome of the F. L. Carroll Chapel and Library on the Baylor University campus in Waco, Texas, caught on fire. Despite the efforts of local firefighters to contain the blaze, flames quickly spread throughout the structure and destroyed the building. At the time, the edifice housed the contents of Baylor’s libraries, including the Browning Library, law library, and the university’s general library holdings. While the structure was completely gutted by the fire, portions of the general collection and the entire Browning and law libraries were preserved through the efforts of students who ran into the burning building and retrieved armfuls of books.
The following month, a twenty-member committee organized to coordinate efforts to rebuild the F. L. Carroll Chapel and Library. They announced that the building would be reconstructed immediately and proposed that the new edifice include a bigger chapel to better accommodate the university’s student body, and a larger library to provide space to grow. The committee assigned the primary concern of fundraising to the Alumni Association, and appealed “to every former student, to every Baptist in Texas, and to all interested friends” to donate or pledge money to the campaign.
The fundraising and rebuilding of F. L. Carroll Chapel and Library did not take long, for on 1923 December 12, the newly rebuilt structure was reopened to the public during a celebration of President Samuel Palmer Brooks’s birthday. Although the reconstruction did not include a chapel as originally had been suggested, it did contain space to house the university’s general library holdings, Browning Library, law library, and the recently acquired Texas Room (now known as the Texas Collection). The building also had a trophy room, several classrooms, and even a courtroom for the law school. Though the uses of the building have changed through the years, the Carroll Library is still in active use today by various Baylor departments.
Scope and Content
The BU Records: Alumni Rebuilding Campaign begins in 1922 February and ends in 1923. Correspondence is the largest series in the collection and consists of letters and telegrams regarding fundraising efforts to rebuild the F. L. Carroll Chapel and Library. The collection also contains financial documents, administrative records, and a program from when the building was reopened in December 1923.
Arrangement
No finding aid existed for the records of the BU Records: Alumni Rebuilding Campaign prior to the creation of this one. The correspondence items in the collection were roughly organized in alphabetical order, according to the last name of the alumni who either sent or received the letters. The few financial and administrative records in the collection were interspersed among the correspondence. While the financial and administrative documents have since been placed in their own separate series, the original order of the correspondence has been preserved.
Currently, the records of the BU Records: Alumni Rebuilding Campaign are arranged in four series: I. Correspondence, II. Financial Documents, III. Administrative Records, IV. Literary Productions.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. BU/58. Acquired 0-00-00
Related Resources
Related references
“Baylor Chapel Lies in Smouldering Ruins.” Baylor Lariat (Waco, TX), 1922 February 11.
“For the Honor of Baylor and the Glory of Texas.” Lariat (Waco, TX), 1922 March 11.
Pool, Helen. “Public Sees Baylor Library At Formal Afternoon Opening.” Baylor Lariat (Waco, TX), 1923 December 12.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor University -- History.; Baylor University -- Alumni and alumnae.; Baylor University -- History -- 20th century.; Baylor University. Carroll Library (Building).
Subjects
Historic buildings -- Texas -- Waco.
Genres
Correspondence.; Financial records.; Programs.
- Correspondence, 1922 February-June, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Average.
  Biography/Profile
  This series is the largest in the collection and contains letters and some telegrams regarding fundraising efforts for the reconstruction of the F. L. Carroll Chapel and Library.
  - To/From Alumni, A-C (1 of 4), 1922 February-May, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - To/From Alumni, A-C (2 of 4), 1922 February-May, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - To/From Alumni, A-C (3 of 4), 1922 February-May, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - To/From Alumni, A-C (4 of 4), 1922 February-May, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - To/From Alumni, C-H (1 of 3), 1922 February-May, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - To/From Alumni, C-H (2 of 3), 1922 February-May, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - To/From Alumni, C-H (3 of 3), 1922 February-May, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - To/From Alumni, H-Y (1 of 2), 1922 March-May, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - To/From Alumni, H-Y (2 of 2), 1922 March-May, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - To/From Alumni, M-S (1 of 3), 1922 March-May, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - To/From Alumni, M-S (2 of 3), 1922 March-May, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - To/From Alumni, M-S (3 of 3), 1922 March-May, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - To/From Alumni, S-Y (1 of 2), 1922 February-June, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - To/From Alumni, S-Y (2 of 2), 1922 February-June, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Financial Documents, undated; 2
  This series contains financial records dealing with fundraising efforts for the reconstruction of the F. L. Carroll Chapel and Library. Items in the series include pledge lists and receipts.
  - Pledge Lists, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Receipts, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "Students' Campaign", undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Administrative Records, undated; 3
  This series contains a document outlining suggested procedures for implementing the Alumni Rebuilding Campaign and a list of “big givers” who had contributed large sums of money to the 75 Million Campaign.
  - "Suggested Procedure For Baylor Rebuilding Campaign", undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - "List of Big Givers to 75 Million Campaign", undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Literary Productions, 1923; 4
  General condition: Good.
  This series contains a 1923 program from when the newly reconstructed F. L. Carroll Chapel and Library reopened.
  - Program: "Housewarming for New Carroll Library", 1923 (Box 2, Folder 12)